<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of Mr. Iohn Cook's passage by sea from Wexford to Kinsale in that great storm Ianuary 5. Wherein is related the strangeness of the storm, and the frame of his spirit in it. Also the vision that he saw in his sleep, and how it was revealed that he should be preserved, which came to pass very miraculously. Likewise a relation of a dream of a Protestant lady in Poland, which is in part come to pass, the remainder being to begin this year 1650. / All written by himself.</title>
            <author>Cook, John, d. 1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80409</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6026A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E598_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206300</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865474</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865474</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117717</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80409)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117717)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 92:E598[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of Mr. Iohn Cook's passage by sea from Wexford to Kinsale in that great storm Ianuary 5. Wherein is related the strangeness of the storm, and the frame of his spirit in it. Also the vision that he saw in his sleep, and how it was revealed that he should be preserved, which came to pass very miraculously. Likewise a relation of a dream of a Protestant lady in Poland, which is in part come to pass, the remainder being to begin this year 1650. / All written by himself.</title>
                  <author>Cook, John, d. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at Cork, and re-printed at London, and are to be sold by T. Brewster and G. Moule at the three Bibles in Pauls church-yard neer the west-end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Apr. 12 1649"; the 50 in imprint date is crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cook, John, d. 1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Voyages and travels --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dreams --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Visions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117717:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRUE RELATION OF M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Iohn Cook's Paſſage by Sea from <hi>Wexford</hi> to <hi>Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſale</hi> in that great Storm <hi>Ianuary</hi> 5. Wherein is Related the Strangeneſs of the Storm, and the Frame of his Spirit in it.</p>
            <p>ALSO The Viſion that he ſaw in his ſleep, and how it was Revealed that he ſhould be preſerved, which came to paſs very miraculouſly.</p>
            <p>LIKEWISE A Relation of a Dream of a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Lady in Poland, which is in part come to paſs, the Remainder being to begin this year 1650.</p>
            <p>All written by himſelf.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Cork,</hi> and Re-printed at <hi>London,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>T. Brewſter</hi> and <hi>G. Moule</hi> at the three Bibles in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard neer the Weſt-End of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:117717:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:117717:2"/>
            <head>A Relation of Mr, <hi>Iohn Cooks</hi> paſſage by Sea from Wexford to Kinſale, being in the great Storm on <hi>Ianuary</hi> the 5.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>The Lord is then beſt praiſed, when we acknowledge him to be his own praiſe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">J</seg>Anuary</hi> the firſt 1649. We embarqued from <hi>Wexford</hi> in the <hi>Hector</hi> for <hi>Corke,</hi> ſayled two or three leagues beyond <hi>Greenor-bay,</hi> but were driven back, the wind turning upon us: upon the Saturday following the wind being fair we got within ſight of <hi>Dungarvan,</hi> that night proved very windy, and about four in the morning, on the Lords day, a very tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wind aroſe, and the ſtorm was the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt that ever any of the Sea-men knew (as they ſaid) the wind was at South-eaſt very thick, we hoped to fetch <hi>Corke,</hi> being within a mile of the ſhore, but could not poſſibly make land: in that diſtreſs we put to ſea, hoping by that way to ſave life, the wind continued all that Sabbath day at South-eaſt, South-eaſt and by South, and ſouth ſouth-eaſt, which if the wind had held at ſouth eaſt as it was in the morning, we could not have doubled the point about the land, but had been caſt upon the rocks: we bore two courſes to keep off from the ſhore all the day, and being as we ſuppoſed about the pitch of the Cape Cleere, at nine on Sabbath day night we ſhipt a great Sea which ſplit and carryed away our foreſaile, and ſo were forced to bring to a fore-top ſail to keep from the ſhore, and ſo bore that fore-tope-ſaile till two in the night, in which time we were forced to cut our Anchor from the bough to ſave the ſhip from foundring, we having at that time five foot water in the hold. The Monday morning we were ten leagues to leeward of the Cape Cleere, and the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117717:3"/>wind was up at South-weſt, then we made all the ſayl poſſible to fetch ſome harbour, and it pleaſed God, we made the Cape, hoping to fetch <hi>Baltamore,</hi> but the wind coming up at South-eaſt and by eaſt, we were forced to Sea again all the night, the wind continuing at ſouth-eaſt, ſouth-eaſt and by ſouth, and ſouth-ſouth-eaſt.</p>
            <p>Tueſday we made the Miſne head and could fetch no harbour the wind being ſtill at ſouth-eaſt. Wedneſday the wind came up at weſt, and we made for ſhore again, and came up as high as <hi>Gally-head</hi> hoping to fetch <hi>Kinſale;</hi> about three in the after-noone the wind came up at eaſt ſouth-eaſt, and then we hoped to recover <hi>Caſtlehaven</hi> before night, and made for it, and in our running in, the wind veared at ſouth-eaſt and blew very freſh, and we ſtill hoping to gain the harbour, ran in, knowing no other way to ſave life, the wind being ſo contrary, it grew extraordinary thick, rained and blew much, we fired three or four pieces of ordnance (for lights) and ſaw one light from the Caſtle, as we ſuppoſed, and two other lights to the Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, which put us to an amazement, not knowing whether they were friends or enemies, and could not poſſibly ſee the going into the Harbor, but were in the very breach of the ſhore, the ſight where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of cauſed a great ſcrick in the ſhip, and thereupon brought our ſhip to, hoping thereby to have come to an Anchor, which if we had done, we had been paſt all hopes of life, the rock being ſo neer would have cut our Anchor, but God being moſt merciful in that nick of time, the ſeamen deſpairing of life, the wind at an inſtant came up at Eaſt, which carried us into the ſea, and yet ſo great was the danger, that if the wind did not turn again to the Weſt in leſs then half an hour, we were dead men, by reaſon of the rocks called the <hi>Staggs,</hi> ſo we came in a little time within ſight of the rocks, the wind driving us ſtrongly upon them, and then ſeeing the rocks within a ſhips length of us, we put our ſhip to ſtay, which ſhe would not the ſea being ſo extremely grown, the Sea-men being at their wits end, wiſhing us to prepare for death: the Lord again at that very inſtant cauſed the wind to come up at South-weſt, which carryed us out into the Sea cleer from the rocks where we had the wind favorable that night, and bleſſed be God on Thurſday we came into <hi>Kinſale,</hi> it being the firſt Harbor that the Lord was pleaſed to give us, but that which is moſt admirable is this, that ſo ſoon as the ſhip was come into <hi>Kinſale</hi> Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, ſhe leaked ſo very much, that the Sea-men came the next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and told us, that they were almoſt drowned that night, and could
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117717:3"/>ſcarce keep the ſhip alive in the Harbor, and were forced the next tide to bring her to the Key, and at the Ebbe to repair her, and had much ado to keep her from ſinking. This being the method of Gods dealing with us in our paſſage,</p>
            <p>Now concerning the work of God upon my ſpirit during the ſtorm, thus it was. Towards the evening of the Sabbath day <hi>January</hi> the 5. my heart was exceeding ſad and ſorrowfull even unto death, a nark night approaching, and the ſhip taking in much water, my ſpirit fainted and my heart ſunk within me, the ſorrows of death caught hold of me, much grieved I was for my poor dear heart who did not expreſs half ſo much fear as my ſelf, many ſweet expreſſions ſhe uſed in prayers, wiſhing me to call earneſtly upon God: many words I could not uſe, but my heart was praying; it almoſt broke my heart to think what my wives friends would ſay in <hi>England,</hi> that I ſhould bring her into <hi>Ireland</hi> to drown her (though I bleſs God ſhe never repined at it) troubled I was likewiſe for my poor ſervants that came in love along with us; it almoſt ſplit my heart to think what the Malignants would ſay in <hi>England</hi> when they hear that we were drowned (how they would abuſe that paſſage of <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 28.4.) That though vengeance hath not overtaken me at Land, yet I was met withall at Sea; much troubled I was at the manner of the death, ſuch extraordinary violent deaths importing the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſome heavy Judgement, as if the Lord had been diſpleaſed with us, and had not ſent us, and <hi>Jonahs</hi> ſtorm was much in my thoughts (I having ſpoken ſome words of Exhortation to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany out of that Scripture before the ſtorm began) for God ſent that great ſtorm, <hi>Jon.</hi> 1.4. becauſe <hi>Jonah</hi> went contrary to his Commands, where I obſerved, That when a Chriſtian is in Gods way, upon Gods errand ſent to Sea, uſually God makes the Winde and the Seas fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable to him; upon ſuch conſiderations, and many objections made by fleſh &amp; blood, I had very much trouble with my unbelieving heart, &amp; could not bring my mind to be willing to die, earneſt I had been in ſecret prayer at the Throne of Grace before, for 16. or 18. hours to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, pleading with the Lord, that if it were poſſible this cup of his indignation might paſs over us, that in Judgments he would remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Mercy, however that we might cheerfully ſubmit to his ſweet pleaſure; the materials of my long ſuggeſted prayers were meditations and applications of ſeverall Scriptures which mention Gods power,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117717:4"/>wiſdome and love in the Seas. God having put it into my minde not long before to note moſt of the chief places in Scripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Seas, as proper and uſefull for a Sea-voyage. I preſt my deere Chriſt not to drown us, for ſaid I, we fight for thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly office, throw the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> and all thy implacable enemies into the midſt of the Sea, but let us be preſerved that we may prayſe thy Name, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.27, 30. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.1. Lord this is a calamity too heavy for thy poor creatures to bear. <hi>Iob</hi> 6.3. were it not that thou haſt caſt our ſinnes into the depths of the Seas: <hi>Micha</hi> 7.19. Lord ſuffer not the deeps to ſwallow us up: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.15. Let not all thy waves and billowes paſſe over us We have ſeen thy wonders in the deep: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.23. And if thou ſave us we ſhall declare them to the children of men; but if thou make our graves in the Sea, the dead cannot praiſe thee: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.17. thou Lord which leadeſt thy ſervants through the deep, prepare dry Land for us: Lord, why ſhould not the Seas be as favorable to thy ſervants as the dry land? Thou layeſt up the depth in ſtorehouſes. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.7. Thou Lord canſt ſtill the noyſe of the waves <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.7. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 68.22. was a comfortable place to me, that the Lord promiſed to bring againe his people from the depth of the Sea. Sweet Chriſt do thy office and be a Saviour to thy people both for ſoules and bodies, thou layeſt the beams of thy Chambers in the waters 10.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3. and ruleſt the raging of the Seas. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.9. Now Lord the floods have lifted up their voyce and their waves: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 93.2. but thou art mightier then the mighty waves of the Sea, The fiſhes of the Sea ſhall ſhrink at thy preſence: but why art thou ſo angry with thy ſervants who are ſent in thy ſervice? Lord caſt the great Dragon into the bottomleſſe pit, that old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent called the Devill and Sathan. <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.9. but let thy people live to prayſe thee; thou Lord canſt ſay to the Sea, Be dry: <hi>Eſa.</hi> 44.27. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 50.2. and canſt eaſily bring us ſafe to land Lord, haſt not thou made the depths of the Sea a way for thy ranſomed ones to paſs over? <hi>Eſa.</hi> 51.10. Why muſt then thy ſervants be drowned as if they were in this malefactors? <hi>Ionah</hi> ran away from thee and would not obey thee, being unwilling to be the mouth and proclaimer of thy Iuſtice upon <hi>Nineveh</hi> the head of the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Empire: and thou ſenteſt out a great winde, and there was a mighty tempeſt in the Sea, <hi>Ionah.</hi> 4. which was no ordinary wind, but ſent as a puniſhment for his diſobedince, yet becauſe he was thy ſervant, and was not ſelviſh,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117717:4"/>nor diſpleaſed in thy ſhewing mercy for feare of his being thought a falſe prophet, but out of zeale for thy glory which he thought was wronged and obſcured by that change, and out of his ardent affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton to thy people that their enemies ſhould live; and though he ſaid, he did well to be angry, even unto death, they being not words of expreſſe rebellion, but of a paſſionate ſpirit blinded with anger, therefore when he prayed unto thee out of the belly of Hell, he was mightily preſerved. Now Lord, thou which waſt a God ſo gracious and merciful ſlow to anger, &amp; of great kindneſs towards the Heathens in <hi>Nineveh</hi> ſhall not we find thy mercy? if thou haſt any further work for us to do in our generation, we ſhall. Lord, it is the wicked that is like the troubled Sea, whoſe water caſts up mire and dirt <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.20. Thy Juſtice was very wonderfull and glorious at <hi>Wexford,</hi> in drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe Pirates and wicked men in the Sea, that had done ſo much miſchief to thy people in that Element, and what will thy enemies ſay when the carkaſſes of thy people are given to be food for the Fiſhes? Lord command this great wind into thy treaſure, and bring forth windes ſerviceable for us that we may have an auſpicious gale, and an expeditious ſaile into ſome Harbor where it ſhall pleaſe thy Majeſty, for thy poor creatures are at their wits end, and death appears in their faces; thou only canſt ſhut up the Sea with doors, <hi>Iob</hi> 38.8. Thou makeſt the deep to boyle like a pot, and makeſt the Sea like a pot of oyntment, as if the Sea was hoary by the long white frothy path, <hi>Job.</hi> 41.31, 32. Sweet Chriſt, thou haſt dominion from ſea to ſea, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.8. and thou haſt given to the ſea a decree, that the waters paſſe not thy commands, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.29. Therefore though the ſea roare and threaten to ſwallow us up, yet unleſs thou giveſt it a commiſſion to devour us it cannot hurt us: ſweet Chriſt, the ſea is unto thee as the dry land, the winds and ſeas will obey thee, deere Redeemer wilt not thou ſpeak one word to ſave the lives of thy own members? <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.26, 27. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.27. <hi>Mark.</hi> 4.29. Peace, Be ſtill, will make a great calme. Lord aſſure ſome of thy poor ſervants that all ſhall be well, as thou didſt to bleſſed <hi>Paul Acts</hi> 27.23. Give ſome viſion and manifeſtation of thy love, for it was for thy ſake that we committed our ſelves to the ſea, let ſome of thy ſervants in the ſhip be aſſured from heaven that we ſhall be ſafe, however Lord let thy will be our wils: with other Scriptures, not now perfectly remembred. Now after long prayers and medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117717:5"/>it pleaſed God about ſix on the Sabboth day night that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt began to quiet my ſpirit in himſelf, and I was well perſwaded to die, and began to be raviſht with the Conſideration of the joyes of Heaven, how quickly I and my poor heart ſhould be in our Maſters joyes, that expreſſion of entring into my Maſters joy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected me much, that the joy was too big to enter into me, I muſt be ſwallowed up in it, and that my Maſters joy could be no ſmall joy; thereupon I ſpake comfortably to my wife, deſiring her to cheer up, for that we ſhould ſuddenly be in Heaven, if the Lord was pleaſed thus to take us to himſelf, who reſigned her ſoul to God, and we took our leaves ſolemnly of each other, with our eyes full of teares, which I felt running down her cheeks when I kiſt them, ſaying that all teares ſhall ſuddenly be wiped from our eyes in Heaven, and with a great fervour of ſpirit I thought ſeverall times to this purpoſe, Sweet Jeſus I come to thee, we come not only in this Sea of waters, but Lord we come to thee in a Sea of blood if it ſhall pleaſe thee to call us; the ſtorm ſtill increaſed, and I grew exceeding heavy and ſleepy, but rouſed my ſelf up, and checked my heart, that I ſhould <hi>Jonah</hi> like offer to ſleep in ſuch a ſtorm: what, be drowned in my ſleep! my wife often begged at me not to ſleep, but I could not poſſibly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear ſleep, if it had been to have ſaved all our lives; ſo it pleaſed God, that ſitting as upright as I could, I fell into as faſt a ſleep as ever I was in all my life.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:117717:5"/>
               <head>And in my ſleep I dreamed.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat I was in an upper chamber with my ſweet Redeemer Chriſt Jeſus, and that there were many Suiters attended to ſpeake with him; to beſeech him to ſave their Ships and Barks that they might not periſh by the ſtorme, I thought it was a large roome, wherein there was a long table with an ordinary Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and two candles ſtanding upon it, two trenchers of Tobacco, and Pipes, and one Man walking up and downe by the toble<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of a middle ſtaturs, about thirty years of age, the hairs of his Head long and white as flax; but curling at the Ends, but the haire of his upper lipp browne, in ſad coulor'd cloathes, and a cloth broad brim'd hatt, I asked him who he was, who ſaid he waited upon Jeſus Chriſt; I asked him where Jeſus Chriſt was, he pointed to a Curtin, ſaying, there he is; I beheld and ſaw a glorious ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning but no perſon, and methought Jeſus Chriſt ſpake to me, and asked me what I would have, I ſaid the lives of all in the Ship, ſaid he in what ſhip ſaid I in the <hi>Hector,</hi> it is a bad name ſaid he, for ſuch as profeſſe me. <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux</hi> is for <hi>Heathens,</hi> I prayed him that we might not dye in this manner, ſayes he to me are not you ſafe? but good Lord ſaid I, I muſt returne, and I beg life for all in the ſhip, who are they ſaid he? I anſwered that there was my deare Wife and three Servants. Lieutenant Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Saunders,</hi> Major <hi>Bee,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hewes,</hi> honeſt <hi>Abraham,</hi> and other paſſingers thy Servants, (ſaid Ieſus Chriſt at my naming Lieu. Col. <hi>Saunders</hi> and ſome others, its ſo much the better that they are there) the Captaine and the Sea-men are ſerviceable to thy Cauſe, and they take wonderfull paines to ſave their owne lives and ours, but unleſſe thou ſpeake the word, the Sea will ſwallow us up. Then me thought Jeſus Chriſt askt me why I was not willing to dye? I told him that by this death I could not glorifie him, thinking upon that Scripture, <hi>Iohn</hi> 21.19. and me thought I was ſomething impatient that the Lord ſhould ſurprize us, get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting us into a ſhip at his call for his Service, and then to drowne us, as if we were Parricides or hainous Malefactors, which by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117717:6"/>Law were drowned: at that me thought Jeſus Chriſt withdrew, as if he was diſpleaſed, ſaid I, Lord, if thou drowneſt thoſe that love thee, what wilt thou doe to thine Enemies? but could get no anſwer, whereupon I was ſenſible of my impatience, and thought that I fell downe flat downe on the ground, and cryed for Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſaying Lord, we kiſſe thy Rod, and turne our naked backs, ſtrike as much as thou pleaſeſt. Lord, I plead nothing but thy free grace; it may be many of us have offended in exceſſive drinking, and now thou art puniſhing us in our owne Element, however our ſinnes are more then the ſands of the Sea-ſhore but let pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty move thee to ſave us; thou ſweet Redeemer which haſt been at Sea in ſtormes, that art a mercifull high Prieſt, like unto us in all things but ſinne. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.17. and 4.15. take pity upon thine owne fleſh and blood; what Father but would ſave his Child from drewning if he could haſt thou no worke for any of us to doe? I thought the anſwer was, but little to be done by ſome of us; (my Wife tells me that but a little before I ſlept, I ſaid, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly God had ſomething for me, and others to doe for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and therefore we ſhould not dye at this time, which I did not remember;) ſweet Chriſt hear us as thou dideſt thy Diſciples ſave us quickly or elſe we periſh, and being earneſt in prayer, in my dreame me thought that the man in the roome came to me, and told me that this was no naturall ſtorme of Gods ſending, but an extraordinary Tempeſt raiſed by Satan (by Gods permiſſion) to deſtroy thoſe which were coming to fight againſt his Servants, and bad me uſe that argument to his Maſter. Thereupon I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly craved leave to ſpeake, and ſaid, ſweet Saviour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if this Storme and Tempeſt be raiſed by Satan the Prince of the ayre as in <hi>Lapland</hi> and many other places where winds are ſold, he works in the Children of diſobedience, and hath nothing to doe with thy poore Servants, for though thou mayſt juſtly for our ſins give Satan power over us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as thou didſt over thy dear Servant <hi>Iob.</hi> Yet where thou giveſt a particular faith to be free from Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans ſtormes and witchcrafts, thou art pleaſed to grant that which is believed, and in great love it pleaſed Jeſus Chriſt to give a gratious anſwer to my Spirit, and ſaid, be not afraid, your lives ſhall be ſaved; inſtantly replyed Lord, let it be for all the Perſons in the Ship He ſaid be it ſo, then I preſſed for the goods in the Ship Lord ſaid I, there are my L. Gen goods, &amp; M. Gn. goods; Let them ſafe, but they are not there ſaid Jeſus Chriſt, no Lord ſaid I, they are fighting thy battells, Jeſus Chriſt anſwered, the goods ſhall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117717:6"/>all be ſafe. And the ſhip likewiſe, and nothing miſcarry, then I gave humble thanks, and departed, and as I was going out, I thought Jeſus Chriſt ſaid to me, it is granted for halfe fifty, goe no more to Sea in winter. I further dream'd that the Devill and his Imps were very earneſt with Jeſus Chriſt to get leave to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Governour of Wexford, by the ſtorme; but the Lord ſaid, it ſhould not be; ſome there were that had Barkes at Wez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, that attended to ſpeake with Jeſus Chriſt, I could not tell what they ſaid, they diſcourſed much about the Governour, and all that I heard Chriſt ſay, was that winter was not yet come for them at Wexford, then I thought I met with Captaine <hi>Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bottell,</hi> who had very great reſpect ſhowne to him, and I thought his prayers did us very much good, and he was very much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for his tenderneſſe to the ſick Souldiers at Wexford, I thought there were other men from Wexford that came for ſafe paſſages, and one Officer was very earneſt for a Ship that he was to come in, and I heard this expreſſion concerning him, we muſt take ſpeciall care of his Ship; for he was very tender and kinde to the poore ſick Souldiers, and much diſcourſe I heard about ſick Souldiers. Jeſus Chriſt ſaid, if ſtormes will not doe, I have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther afflictions to make them more tender-hearted and pitifull, me thought the perſon that ſo walked in the roome, ſpake much to this effect, that there would be many ſtormes by reaſon of much hardheartedneſſe, to breake and melt their Spirits, ſince which (bleſſed be God) Captaine <hi>Lucus</hi> is come ſafe in the wild <hi>Beare,</hi> one whom I obſerved in Wexford to be very liberall, tender-hearted, and compaſſionate to the poore Souldiers, whereupon I awaked, this dreame laſted about two houres, all which time the ſtorme encreaſed, my Wife told me, that ſhee jogged me above twenty times to waken me. And wondred that I ſhould ſleep, ſeeing we were all ſo neere the point of death, ſaid I to her, peace my dear heart, be quiet, we ſhall all be ſafe: Jeſus Chriſt hath promiſed me our lives, be not afraid, and told her all my dreame, whereat ſhe was much amazed, but could not believe any afety, and urged me to prayer, being her ſelfe well reſolved to dye, cheerefully ſubmitting to Gods good pleaſure, but told me ſhe had a ſtrong impreſſion upon her Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit by way of queſtion, as if the Lord had ſpoken to her, that in caſe he ſhould be pleaſed to ſpare her life at this time, whether ſhe could be content to ſuffer for him, whereunto ſhe found her heart moſt ready and willing, by the Lords aſſiſtance, to lay
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117717:7"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owne her life for his glory; but my owne heart was then giving thanks and bran full of comfort.</p>
               <p>I related my dreame to Lieutenan Col. <hi>Saunders,</hi> Major <hi>Bee, Ben.</hi> and the two Maids that were in the Cabin. And ſent in for Captaine <hi>Stoakes,</hi> the Maſter the Gunner, <hi>Bennet,</hi> and marſhall and bad them be of good cheere, and plye their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for we ſhould be all ſafe, telling them what I had dream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they admired at my confidence, and Captaine <hi>Stoakes</hi> could not believe it, (ſaid he) I know God is very Mercifull and can doe much; but the Ship hath five foot water in the hould which the Pumpe could not reach being choaked, and very ſubject to leaks, being twenty years old, and then it was about nine at night, the ſtorme increaſing, and they not knowing where about they were, I told them that I was aſſured of ſafety, as if I were on Shore and one word more I had dreamed, which I told them of ſaid I to Jeſus Chriſt, what if the Ship ſhould break aſunder? He anſwered me, you ſhall be as ſafe as if you were in <hi>Codds</hi> Boat (a Boat at Wexford that we went in towards the ſhip in the bay, and were driven back ſeverall times) or as if you were in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors houſe in Wexford what impreſſion it had upon their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits I know not, but ſome that were in the great Cabbin told me that they did verily beleeve it, and that their hearts were much quieted by what I ſaid. The ſtorme increaſed and a great noyſe was made in the ſhip, the water came in at the great Cabbine windowes, the ſhip ready to overſet and to founder; many skreaks and cryes out now we are gone, and yet my confidence and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance increaſed, I bad them pray and bethankfull for they were as ſafe as if they were on ſhoare ſtill my poore Wife ſaid it could not be I told her I was ſure of it; ſhe muſt lye ſtill and ſee the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our God.</p>
               <p>I confeſſe I much marvelled at the change that was wrought in my own Spirit, from a trembling fearfulneſſe to a rejoycing aſſurance and conſidering it was but a dreame I thought I might preſume too much in an over Confidence and was jealous over my owne hart leaſt I ſhould offend, begging the Lords extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary aſſiſtance ſutable to the preſent danger, but the more I checkt my heart of preſumption; the more did my faith mount upon the wing as if I had been upon dry ground, and had not ſo much fear as the thouſand part of the weight of a haire: the poor ſhip workt for her life, and the Sea-men took infinite paines, two parts being fallen ſick &amp; the other 30. were continually at it, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117717:7"/>they were in a little hopes, ſometimes their Soules ready to faint about twelve at night, he that was at the Helme by my Cabbin ſaid all was broken, the water came in there, a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they cryed out, that the foreſaile was ſplit and carried away, and the Anchors thrown over board to lighten the ſhip, yet all this while my Spirit was the ſame in a thankfull admiration, for ſo great a deliverance, and ſaid, all ſhall be as well as heart could wiſh, when they ſpoke of lightning the ſhip, my wife cald to Capt. <hi>Stoaks</hi> and bad him if he thought fit to throw over ſome Trunkes which we had in the ſhip, which I like very well (as it was in <hi>Pauls</hi>-ſtorm) in regard of others that were in the ſhip, but for my own part, I ſaid I would not have any thing throwne over, for I knew all would be well and (ſo bleſſed be the Lord of Seas) about four in the morning, the ſtorme abated, my heart was in a very thankfull poſture, and that Wedneſday night after, when the Sea-men ſaid, we were in moſt danger entring into <hi>Caſtle-Haven</hi> in the dark, that we muſt have the wind turne twice in halfe an houre to ſave us, firſt to carry us from the breach of the ſhoare to the <hi>Staggs,</hi> and then to carry us off from them: when we were within a Cables length of the ſhoare, and the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men devided, not knowing what to do Captaine <hi>Stoakes</hi> bad let fall an Anchor, or elſe we are all dead-men others ſaib, try to get off from ſhoare, and there was a great skreak that all was gone, I was not one jot afraid, but told them they were ſure to get ſafe to Land, and the ſhip to a Harbour, and the Lord ſhewed himſelfe kind to poore ſinners.</p>
               <p>One thing though it ſeeme to be of ſmall importance, yet it runs much in my mind, and I muſt needs relate it. I thought that Jeſus Chriſt ſaid to me that the goods ſhould be all ſafe, and nothing hurt or loft by the ſtorme, but when we came to look for our things we miſt a looking-glaſſe and a Piſtoll, the glaſſe caſe was all broke and ſhivered in many peeces by the rouling of the ſhip, being in one of the Boxes or Cabin-cheſts in the great Cabbin amongſt other things but the Glaſſe it ſelfe was not ſo much as broken or crackt and the caſe though in eight or ten peeces yet might eaſily be joyned and glued together, that it is not worſe by a farthing, which ſeemes to me very admirable, I told Captaine <hi>Stoakes</hi> of it, and deſired him, if poſſible, to help me to my Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoll, he examined them about it; but it could not be heard of, till the very day the ſhip was going out of the Harbour, and then ſomebody that had it could not be quiet till he brought it out,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117717:8"/>to let us ſee how weak our faith and confidence is in the Lord and that he will performe with his poore ſervants to a Title of his promiſe.</p>
               <p>I know that uſually dreames follow mens naturall inclination or their daily converſation, as in <hi>Pharaohs Butler</hi> and <hi>Baker,</hi> they dreamed of wine and baskets of meate, matters about which they were ordinarily imployed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 40. and I having beene in a continued meditation of Jeſus Chriſt his love, power, bowells of pitty towards his members, it was moſt likely, that if I dreamed of any thing I ſhould dreame of him as mary times upon the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boths nights: I have dreamed that I was in the very ſame company and at the ſame exerciſes as I was upon the day, and indeed the conſideration of Chriſts humanity his being at Sea, and his experimentall knowledge of our miſeries much ſupported me, how many prayers did we put up for a ſafe paſſage which though they do not move the Lord by any eloquence, as an Orator moves his hearers, yet they move the Lord; as the cryes of children make the bowels of thelr Parents yearne towards them, and we muſt diſtinguiſh between ſhadowes and ſubſtances, dreames are but the appearances of things which are not, naturall dreams are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinfull, deceitfull &amp; vaine, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.8. the hungry thirſty man dreames, that he eats and drinks, but he awakes and his ſoule is faint for food, or elſe they are repreſentations of things paſt which were really done or things to come which falls out accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly and the matter of the dreame is principally to be regarded, ſome Chriſtians have had difficult places of Scripture expounded to them in their dreames, as they have told me.</p>
               <p>Therefore although dreames which are naturall and ordinary be of little or no account yet extraordinary dreames many times prove true, as if one cry in his dream or be ſo faſt aſlcep that he feels not pinching when the Imagination is ſo extraordinarily powerfull, and that the party dreaming is confidently perſwaded that it will come to paſſe it commonly proves accordingly as that of <hi>Katherin de Medicis</hi> Queen of France, who dreamed that <hi>Hen.</hi> the Second, ſhould be killed at the Tilt, and ſaid ſhe would venture her ſoule upon it. And ſo he was killed by a Scots man, <hi>Montgomery</hi> as ſhe dreamed; <hi>Petrarch</hi> in <hi>Pado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va</hi> dreamed that a <hi>Scorpion</hi> ſtung him to death, that was in one of the Lyons that ſtand before a ſtatue which they fondly call <hi>Sancta Iuſtina,</hi> the next morning he told his dreame, went thither and put in his hund into the hole and out came a Scorpion which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117717:8"/>poyſoned him, whereof he dyed, the great Souldier <hi>Fareſe</hi> the night before he dyed; dreamed that he was drowned and that his Saint <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> could not carry him over the River and the next day the Ferry-boat ſunk and he was drowned.</p>
               <p>In 1629. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> a Proteſtant Marqueſſes Daughter in <hi>Poland,</hi> dreamed that Jeſus Chriſt had told her comfortable things for the Proteſtants, as the good ſucceſſe of the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> the death of the Emperors Generall <hi>Walſton</hi> and that it might be the better believed, ſhe ſhould dye four dayes and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive againe, one Miniſter <hi>Cotu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nius</hi> ſlighted it as a deluſion and vaine fancie, ſhe told him that God was angry with him, and ſuch a day his only child ſhould dye and himſelfe preſently after, which both proved true, ſhe likewiſe fell into a Trance for eight and fourty houres and then revived and foretold victories of the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> but that God would take him away, becauſe the people began to make a God of him and thought him to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible. She dreamed that ſhe was married to Jeſus Chriſt, and that ſhe had a Crown of Glory promiſed her if ſhe could perſevere in the faith, and told her ſhe would be mockt and ſcoft at by many who would not believe but that ſuch viſions procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from imagination, melancholly humours or weakneſſe of braine, but bad her not be d ſcouraged, ſhewing her a cup of blood, which he ſaid he would poure upon thoſe that perſecute his ſervants, and that ſhe prayed very earneſtly for the ſalvation of a deerfriend of hers who was in armes againſt the Proteſtants, but that ſhee could not prevaile for the ſalvation of any of her friends, but only for her ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fe and that night the ſame party d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, ſhe likewiſe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er dreame ſaw two great perſons comming to be judged one a Papiſt who had pray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o his St. <hi>Francis</hi> and deſired to be admitted into Heaven, but Jeſus Chriſt bad him go to H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aint <hi>Francis,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he was immediatly dragged; and the other was a Prow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> who argued for his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, becauſe he fought againſt the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, and the Miniſters aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured him of Heaver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Jeſus Chriſt ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e will put out his candle in Germany, for it gives a fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> light, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> without but it is full of filth and ſelfe righteouſneſſe with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> likewiſe ſaw a man upon a Tree adored by many; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lyons came to the Tree and pluckt it down, and an Eagle was flying away, which the Lyons caught, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oare in pieces, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>king Jeſus Chriſt the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117717:9"/>meaning of that viſion, he told, that that the man was that horrid beaſt the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> my capitall enemy, not a Paſtor, but a Woolfe, that ſayes, behold I am ſet aloft, who dare come to touch me? the Lyons are the <hi>French, Engliſh, Sweads, Hollanders, Venetians,</hi> and others that ſhall pluck down the proud beaſt, and powre out my wrath upon her and her adherents, and tha it ſhould begin about 1650. and be compleat by 1666. in her ſleep ſhe was heard to ſay; welcome Husband, and laughed heartily and as ſhee awaked ſhee ſaid farewell deere Husband, and ſhe drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med many thing more which fell out accordingly, being a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuos child naturally merry</p>
               <p>In 1633. ſhe was marryed in <hi>Leſno</hi> in <hi>Poland,</hi> and moſt of the Miniſters in <hi>Germany</hi> have ſubſcribed to it, for they ſeriouſly conſulted about it, and ſent into <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Geneva,</hi> for aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and adviſe, and the reſult of the conference (which Mr. <hi>Deodate</hi> ſhewed me at <hi>Geneva</hi>) came to this; in <hi>Chriſtinaes</hi> dreame, they did believe there was a divine light: for firſt the young Lady was regenerate, and very zealous for the glory of God, ſo there was a good life in the perſon dreaming: Secondly, there was a full perſwaſion of heart that it was from God, and it would prove true: Thirdly, there was a certitude in the event, the party was not deceived, for it proved ſo, and it was likewiſe their judgements, that in a time of generall perſecution, or ſome extraordinary eminent danger, God might and did many times ſpeake comfortable things to his people in dreames, as in the late <hi>Bohemian</hi> warres, many <hi>Calviniſts</hi> were admoniſht in their dreames to goe to places of ſecurity, which they attending were ſafe from the enemy; as the Angell of the Lord appeared to <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> in a dreame, and bad him flee with Jeſus Chriſt into <hi>Egypt, Mat.</hi> 2.13. and others that heglected ſuch dreames have after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards repented it.</p>
               <p>The Lord keep us all that were made partakers of ſo great a mercy in an humble believing and thankfull poſture, that we may ſpend the remainder of our new lives in the zeale of his ſervice, as thoſe that having their lives prolonged ſo extraordinarily are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly obliged more then othhers to walk anſwerably to ſo great a mercy.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
